Mazal tov
מזל טוב. Mazal Tov. Today's 26 days of the Omer עומר Omer
and Daf Chaf דף כ Daf Chaf of Me'ilah מעילה. Meilah. We
have two days left of Me'ilah מעילה, Meilah, believe it or not.
It's like it seems like we just got started. Yeah. I mean
finally we're getting into the meat of it. Now we're getting into
what's Me'ilah מעילה.
Meilah. Yeah, like what's Me'ilah מעילה. Meilah. What's Me'ilah מעילה. Meilah. But
you know this is not the first Masechet מסכת Masechet where we've
not gotten to the...
I know. All right, so we pick up with the Mishnah משנה
Mishnah on the bottom of Yud Tet Amud Bet יט עמוד ב.
Yud Tet Amud Bet. So we've been talking about the forms of
Me'ilah מעילה, Meilah, the acts about deriving benefit through some type of
pegam פגם, pegam, things that have pegam פגם pegam with them, or
we haven't yet really spoken about appropriation, that's actually coming up in
this Mishnah משנה. Mishnah. And we've talked about how the act of
Me'ilah מעילה Meilah
violates the Kedusha קדושה, Kedusha, so it causes the Kedusha קדושה Kedusha
to disappear. There's מעל מעלתם Na'al Me'altem with the exception of things
that have Kedushas HaGuf קדושת הגוף, Kedushas HaGuf, that have intrinsic Kedusha
קדושה Kedusha like a Korban קרבן Korban or Kli Shareis כלי שרת.
Kli Shareis. So now we pick up with the Mishnah משנה Mishnah
on the bottom of Yud Tet Amud Bet יט עמוד ב Yud
Tet Amud Bet where we get to finally the Me'ilah מעילה Meilah
of or appropriation. Let's take a look. Or stealing. Natalt Even O
Karah נטל אבן או קורה, Natalt Even O Karah, if somebody takes
a stone or beam shel Hekdesh של הקדש, shel Hekdesh, Harei Zeh
Lo Ma'al הרי זה לא מעל, Harei Zeh Lo Ma'al, you have
not yet done Me'ilah מעילה. Meilah. Ad Nesano Lechavero עד שנתנה לחברו,
Ad Nesano Lechavero, if you gave it to your friend, Hu Ma'al
הוא מעל, Hu Ma'al, you did the Me'ilah מעילה, Meilah, Vechavero Lo
Ma'al וחברו לא מעל, Vechavero Lo Ma'al, not your friend. Now why?
Where's the act of Me'ilah מעילה Meilah here? So this in most
simply is the Me'ilah מעילה Meilah of like taking possession, stealing, taking
out of Hekdesh's הקדש's Hekdesh control into your control. Now why is
the very act of taking not itself Me'ilah מעילה? Meilah? The Gemara
גמרא Gemara will discuss, but as I've already pointed out to you,
the Gemara's גמרא's Gemara going to make it a special case. But
I've already pointed out to you, you know, if you sneak into
Hekdesh's הקדש's Hekdesh warehouse and take something, that's one thing. But you
could imagine a case where you sanctified a beam. So you sanctified
the beam to give to Hekdesh הקדש Hekdesh and now you took
it. Well what does that mean you took it from Hekdesh הקדש?
Hekdesh? I mean you had intent to keep it, that's enough.
So here what it focuses on... anyway the Gemara's גמרא's Gemara going
to make it a special case as we'll see in the Gemara
גמרא, Gemara, but it's not always easy to define what does it
mean to steal from Hekdesh הקדש. Hekdesh. But once you if you
take it and then you give it to somebody else, that's clearly
you're taking it away from where it belongs and you're getting it
out of Hekdesh's הקדש's Hekdesh control and you are stealing it, you
are appropriating it. Now why did your friend not mo'el מועל? mo'el?
Because you're fundamentally the one to have done the act of stealing
and removing, not your friend. If your friend were to benefit from
it afterwards, would he or she be mo'el מועל? mo'el? No, because
Ain Me'ilah Achar Me'ilah אין מעילה אחר מעילה Ain Me'ilah Achar Me'ilah
like we learned in the previous Mishnah משנה. Mishnah. So as soon
as you're the one that's mo'el מועל, mo'el, it takes it out
of Hekdesh הקדש Hekdesh and therefore he doesn't have to get it
out of his house.
Like let's say I've designated a place for it in my place
so, you know, you can come take it whenever you want and
it's still in my backyard. Am I mo'el מועל mo'el then? Well
we're going actually get a case something like that in a second.
It's actually later in the Mishnah משנה. Mishnah. So let's take a
look at that. Now one interesting thing to think about by the
way, this question about what exactly defines an act is to compare
it to a case of Shlichus Yad שליחות יד Shlichus Yad by
a
Pikadon פקדון. Pikadon. If Michael gives me something of his to watch,
so if I'm sholeiach yad שולח יד, sholeiach yad, if I try
to appropriate it, then I become liable for any of the losses.
Well what does it mean that I try to appropriate it? I
move it from one place to the other? I think that I'm
going to take it for myself? Okay, so there's also there's cases
where like you might have something under your control but it's not
yours and what do you define the act of taking. But clearly
when you finally give it to somebody else, that's considered Me'ilah מעילה.
Meilah. Now
is this a different type of Me'ilah מעילה Meilah than the one
before? As I've been saying all along, it does make sense to
think that this is a different at least way of being mo'el
מועל. mo'el. It's not about deriving benefit, it's about actually appropriating. Now
we have learned before presumably different forms of Me'ilah מעילה Meilah can
combine. So they're not that different. If I take do this with
a half of a prutah פרוטה prutah and nehene נהנה nehene from
a half of a prutah פרוטה prutah that combine, so in some
conceptual way it's the same. But still this is more about appropriating
than it is about benefit. Some people try to really collapse them
and to say that here you are nehene נהנה nehene because since
you give it to your friend, that ultimately is a type of
way that you are deriving benefit from the object because you're giving
him this thing, that's a way you benefit from objects, you dispose
of them and you get to use them as you see fit.
But more simply it is not about Hana'ah הנאה, Hana'ah, it is
about a type of Me'ilah מעילה Meilah that we have not really
focused on until now, that of taking and stealing. And the question
is at what stage is it considered that you've stolen, that you've
taken.
Because this is a case where you didn't sneak into Hekdesh הקדש.
Hekdesh. Right and we'll be mo'el מועל mo'el right away then?
Right and we'll see that in the Gemara גמרא. Gemara. Okay. Now
uvenaso betoch beiso ובנאה בתוך ביתו, uvenaso betoch beiso, let's say you
built it into your house, Harei Zeh Lo Ma'al הרי זה לא
מעל Harei Zeh Lo Ma'al until you derive a prutah פרוטה prutah
of Hana'ah הנאה. Hana'ah. Ad Sheyehene Mimenu Beshveh Prutah עד שיהנה ממנו
בשוה פרוטה. Ad Sheyehene Mimenu Beshveh Prutah. Then until you derive a
prutah פרוטה prutah of Hana'ah הנאה Hana'ah you have not derived benefit.
Now that seems crazy, I built it into my house! But it's
really saying the same point that it says before. Somehow it's not
stealing just by you taking it. You have to do something with
it. You have to either give it out to somebody else or
build it in your house and get Hana'ah הנאה, Hana'ah, which is
the Me'ilah מעילה Meilah of Hana'ah הנאה. Hana'ah. The Gemara's גמרא's Gemara
going to ask the obvious question which is two questions. Number one
is isn't the building of the house... more than enough to say
that I've stolen it if stealing is really a form of מעילה?
me'ilah? And number two, if I build it into my house and
even before I've lived under it, haven't I נהנה ne'heneh that now
my house is improved? I have a better house, I fixed up
my house. Okay, so we will talk about that in the גמרא.
Gemara. Now נתנו לבלן, nasnu l'balan, this might have been Michael's case,
not exactly. You gave it to the, you gave it to the
בלן balan which is the basically the guy in charge of the
bathhouse. Okay, so you stole a, presumably not a beam, whatever it
is, you took something, money from הקדש hekdesh and you gave it
to the bathhouse attendant. Now אף על פי שלא רחץ מעל, af
al pi she'lo rachatz ma'al, even though you did not yet bathe,
you have been מועל. mo'el. Why?
Because maybe the point is well why isn't that just stealing the
beam and giving it to somebody else? Well because you might think
that as long as you haven't bathed, you know, you can get
your money back. So maybe the transaction isn't complete, right? If I
give you something as a gift, as soon as I give it
to you the transaction is complete. If I'm
buying a cow from you, when I give you the money and
you haven't given me the cow, the transaction isn't complete. So maybe
I haven't been מועל mo'el yet because I haven't yet given it
out, right? We haven't finished the transaction. But no, when you give
it to the guy in front of the bathhouse, even if you've
yet to bathe, you have been מועל. mo'el. Why? שהוא אומר לו
she'hu omer lo because the bathhouse attendant says to you הרי המרחץ
פתוח לפניך הכנס ורחוץ, harei ha'merchatz patuach lefanecha hachneis u'rechoitz,
hey,
you know, you paid for your entrance fee, the bathhouse is open,
go in and bathe. So basically the transaction is complete because you
now have the right to enter in and bathe. Even if you
haven't bathed, you actually have bought the, you've paid the entrance fee
and you have the right to enter. So that does make the
transaction complete. Okay, so these are three forms that taking something is
itself not הקדש, hekdesh, not מועל mo'el until you give it out.
So the first case and the last case are the most similar,
but just you have to complete the transaction. Or in the case
where you didn't give it out, you have to actually derive benefit
even if you build it in your house. So the question is
of course going to be why certainly in the middle case, but
why are these not just acts of taking even before you've given
it out?
So this is really neat, you know, it's not exactly Michael's case,
my case is I give it to you as a gift, but
I didn't actually give it to you yet, I say you can
go and take it whenever you want.
Right, right, so you're saying let's say you did it through קנין
חליפין kinyan chalipin or some type of halachic way that actually transferred
it without actually physically moving its space. Right, קנין חצר, kinyan chatzer,
קנין חליפין, kinyan chalipin, something like that. I would assume that's the
same, I would assume that's נתינה. nesinah.
But even let's say you didn't do a קנין, kinyan, you say
here it's yours, just go, you can come take it.
No,
that's not halachically meaningful. No, that's meaningful. Even if I like sort
of hypothecate to you, I say, you know, it's yours, just go
and take it. Yeah, but it's like the הוה אמינא hava amina
by the בלן. balan. If you don't, if it's not really a
binding type of a transaction, even though the whole thing isn't binding
anyway because you're stealing it, okay, but actually it's an interesting question,
once you're מועל mo'el then does it become yours, what happens to
the הקדש, hekdesh, you know, because the קדושה kedusha goes off, but
anyway, no, but it has to, in order to be a meaningful
action it has to be an action that otherwise would be legally
binding, okay, not just סתם stam words.
Yeah, this is different than stealing from a person, isn't it? If
you can't steal from me and then take that money and if
I want it back you're liable, right? Right, right, absolutely. So the
laws of הקדש hekdesh have nothing to do with regular theft.
Well you are liable to pay back, right? That's the whole הלכה
halacha of מעילה me'ilah is that you have to pay back plus
adding a חומש. chomesh. But the idea that you can appropriate it
and get
benefit, if you steal from me even if you don't use it,
you leave it in your yard, it's still theft.
Right, right, that is correct. But let's take a look at the
first line of the גמרא Gemara because the גמרא Gemara is going
to ask why you need that extra step. So let's look at
the first line of the גמרא Gemara about that and then we'll
get back to Rivka's question. Okay, so now the גמרא, Gemara, I
do, I do also want to say though which I thought you
were also asking which is I think which is not clear from
the גמרא, Gemara, which is there's no מועל אחר מועל mo'el achar
mo'el because the קדושה kedusha goes away, but does that also mean
that I now own it? Right, because those ideas about הקדש hekdesh
owning it and the object having sanctity are linked, but they can
exist, they can be independent. Right, so when I go ahead and
I מועל mo'el by this beam, does it now belong to me?
Right, that I think is, you know, not spelled out by the
principle of אין מועל אחר מועל. ein mo'el achar mo'el. Let's, let's
see the rest of the משנה Mishnah and then we'll, the גמרא
Gemara will go back to Rivka's question. Okay, so the משנה Mishnah
says like this. This is a point that we said before and
it's really not going to be analyzed in the גמרא. Gemara.
אכילתו ואכילת חבירו הנייתו והניית חבירו, achilaso v'achilas chaveiro hanayaso v'hanayas chaveiro,
if you're eating and your friend's eating, you're benefiting and your friend's
benefiting, אכילתו והניית חבירו, achilaso v'hanayas chaveiro, you're eating and your friend's
benefiting, הנייתו ואכילת חבירו, hanayaso v'achilas chaveiro, you're benefiting and your friend's
eating, מצטרפין זה עם זה, mitztarfin zeh im zeh, all of those
combined, ואפילו לזמן מרובה, v'afilu l'zman merubeh, even after a lot of
time. That's the basic principle that it's not like an act of
eating where it's only you and it's only תוך כדי אכילת פרס
toch kedei achilas pras and it's only כזית. kezayis. Here it's about
a פרוטה, perutah, it's over a long period of time and even
now when your friend, now that doesn't mean your friend did his
own act and then because obviously then that's his מעילה. me'ilah. What
it means is that you go ahead and you're the one to
have done the act of taking. So you take the oil and
you put it on your friend, and that type of a thing
is your מעילה meilah and therefore it combines even though it's your
friend is the recipient and that combines over a period of time
which, given that the that it ends, I should say, with that
phrase going back to the concept of אכילה achilah and הנאה hana'ah
would be a reason to think that this idea of stealing is
being conceived of as a form of הנאה hana'ah specifically when we
also say it includes הנאת חבירו. hana'as chaveiro. So then you can
say that when I give Michael you the bean, why I am
being I am being מועל moel because I am benefiting you. You
are receiving an object of a פרוטה perutah so the same way
if I took הקדש hekdesh oil and put it on your skin,
that would be my מעילה. meilah. I took it away from הקדש
hekdesh and you received the הנאה hana'ah but it's my מעילה. meilah.
I take the bean from הקדש hekdesh I give it to you.
It's my מעילה. meilah. So that is definitely one way of understanding
this and that would actually say that there is not a concept
of stealing of מעילה. meilah. It always requires this concept of הנאה
hana'ah except in these cases it is the הנאה hana'ah of the
recipient. So that is a very important conceptual question: are there these
two approaches or fundamentally just one? Yes.
This is different from שבת shabbos where if two people jointly for
instance carry something.
Right, then they're both פטור. patur.
Yeah, it's not that it's permitted but they they're not חייב chayav
at the biblical level.
Right. So first of all there's a question about how does that
play out when it's talking about ממונות mamonos like גזילה, gezeilah, right,
because two people steal something it's not like you can't collect your
money back. And here we the we are I have been framing
this very clearly that one person
is
the מועל moel is active and the other is just the passive
recipient. Okay, but what if two people somehow stole it together, stole
the bean together? Then it would be a question about do you
is this a concept of stealing or הנאה hana'ah and how do
you conceptualize that? Okay, let's take a look now at the גמרא.
gemara. Now the גמרא gemara here asks the basic question which is
why can't you just steal before you've given it out? Okay, מאי
שנא הוא מאי שנא חבירו, mai shna hu mai shna chaveiro, what
difference does it make if it's you or your friend? Why does
it have to wait until you give it to your friend in
order to be stealing? So אמר שמואל, amar shmuel, so שמואל shmuel
says בגזבר המסורות לו עסקינן. begizbar hamesuros lo askinan.
We're talking about the temple treasurer that has the right to be
using all of these materials. So for the temple treasurer, right, he
can't for him picking something up even with the intent to take
is not yet stealing. Stealing is only when he actually gives it
to somebody else. Now of course you could imagine maybe stealing is
when he sneaks it out of the temple and brings it home
like the person that's working in the storeroom, right, he might have
a right to handle all the stuff but you stick it in
your pocket and you go home with it, that's already stealing, right?
You could have imagined that. But somehow it's saying no that since
somehow conceptually you always have a right to be handling this if
you're the treasurer, it's only considered an act of taking away when
you give it to somebody else. But that's when I also describe
scenarios where I think would be the same as in my house.
If you sanctify an object in your house and the temple hasn't
picked it hasn't picked it up yet, you could certainly imagine that
conceptually that's in a way that's even that's even harder to be
stealing because by the temple treasurer like I said he could sneak
it out of the temple and bring it home. Here the thing
is already in your house. What would define an act of stealing?
But that's basically the way the גמרא gemara conceptualizes it is if
you basically have rights to this to be handling this thing, it's
not yet stealing until you take it away and the taking it
away is the giving to the to somebody else. Okay, so does
that somewhat answer your question רבקה? rivka? Oh yeah, okay. So that's
the basic idea of you have to give it out. But again,
as I said, is that because of stealing or is that because
of a concept of הנאה? hana'ah? It seems like it's an idea
of stealing. Now we get to the hard middle case which is
the house. Why by the house isn't building it in my house
even if I am the temple treasurer, isn't that a little bit
of a misappropriation? So let's take a look at what the גמרא
gemara says. בנאה בתוך ביתו bna'ah besoch beiso and you're
not חייב, chayav, build it in your house you're not liable until
you actually live under it and get a הנאה hana'ah from it.
למה לי עד דידור תחתיה? lama li ad deyidur sachteha? Why do
I need to live under it? כיון דשני מעל, keivan deshni ma'al,
once you changed it you were מועל. moel. Now some have the
גרסא girsa instead of דשני deshni if you look at the אלף
aleph in brackets דבנאה. devna'ah.
Okay, the little שיטה מקובצת shita mekubetzes here in the leftmost. Once
you built it into your house you were מועל. moel. Now it
might be saying דשני deshni for the following reason, because if the
idea is that it's hard to see me stealing since I have
rights to be using this, so if I just put it on
the top on my house which is actually what the גמרא gemara
is going to answer, maybe that's not a taking it if I
haven't done it's just sitting there. But if I actually changed it,
I hammered it in, I plastered it, right, that's a real act
of taking possession. So that seems to be whether the גרסא girsa
is changed it or built it, that seems to be the point.
If you've actually done something physically, built it in, that's a real
taking of possession, you should not need to have to live under
it. So the גמרא gemara says let's see אמר רב, amar rav,
so רב rav says כגון שהניחה על פי ארובה. kegon shehenicha al
pi aruba.
So basically no you didn't change it. You basically you had a
sunroof and you basically and it was, you know, you had a
hole in your thing and you laid it on top and you
haven't permanently built it in. Maybe it's raining or something, you don't
want things to get wet, so you made it like a cover
atop of a sunroof. But you didn't actually build it into the
house and therefore it's not yet taking it until you derive הנאה.
hana'ah. Now look, even there of course we would intuitively say look,
you know, it's like the גזבר gizbar sneaking something out in his
pocket. Even if you have a right to handle it, you still
are now basically appropriating. But no, what the גמרא Gemara is saying
is that's not yet take it. That's using. If you basically have
this and you put it on your roof and you haven't built
it in, you're now using something that doesn't belong to you and
using it means you got some הנאה, hana'ah, you got some benefit.
But you haven't yet taken it until you actually, you know, give
it to somebody else. And therefore that is how it is explained
in the משנה. Mishnah. Yes, I know it's not the פשט pshat
of the word בנאה. banah. Not at all.
It's because it's the exact opposite.
I know, the משנה Mishnah seems to be emphasizing that even if
you do really take possession, you still, right, it's not enough. But
the גמרא Gemara is pulling the brakes of the משנה, Mishnah, also
seems to say that even for a normal person you're never מעול
mo'el when you take something, and the גמרא Gemara says it doesn't
make any sense. Right, so the גמרא Gemara is definitely putting some
brakes on this by this idea.
Okay, so that's what we have. We have that stealing is a
form of מעילה me'ilah unless you try to reframe it as הנאה
hana'ah which might be the emphasis of the משנה Mishnah why the
משנה Mishnah is more, seems to be more cases than the גמרא,
Gemara, but it seems that the גמרא Gemara is saying stealing is
it, it is. But some people have a right to handle it
and it's not stealing till they give it out. And if you
just haven't really yet complete changed it, you just placed it on
your roof, then you're using it but you're not yet stealing it
and you have to get הנאה. hana'ah.
But wouldn't it be the same like let's say, you know, oh
this is a beautiful beam, I'm going to put it in my
display case and then look at it, would we say that's not
considered הנאה? hana'ah?
Well, aesthetic הנאה hana'ah is not הנאה. hana'ah. Okay, so it has
to be things that are really halachically defined as הנאה. hana'ah. So
now it says like
this, אמר רב, Amar Rav, oh we did that. Okay, so now
the
גמרא Gemara has it, now the גמרא Gemara has a side question.
Okay, for us מעילה, me'ilah, like, you know, this is the heart
of the act of מעילה, me'ilah, but the גמרא Gemara is not
fully unpacking it, the גמרא Gemara is now going to go to
a side question. גמרא Gemara says like this, וכיון דבני ליה
מאתמול, ve-kivan de-banei lei mei-etmol, so okay, you're saying once you do
finally build it or could have said once you live under it,
but either once you once you actually knock, bang it into your
your roof, you know, you actually really build it or you get
הנאה, hana'ah, that is מעילה. me'ilah. Alright. לימא מסייע ליה לרב, lei-ma
misayeia lei le-Rav,
so this should support רב, Rav, דאמר רב de-amar Rav המשתחוה לבית
אסרו. ha-mishtachaveh le-bayit assaro.
If somebody worships a house, bows down to a house, he makes
it forbidden. Why is it relevant? Because the question here is a
very important question in a lot of areas of הלכה halacha that
distinguish between things that are connected, that are chattel מטלטלין metaltelin and
קרקע. karka. How do you define something that starts as מטלטלין metaltelin
and then gets built into the ground? Okay, like a house. Is
a house קרקע karka or is a house מטלטלין? metaltelin? So רב
Rav says, right, you understand, right, it starts off with a lot
of wood and stones or whatever, but now it's connected to the
ground. So רב Rav says it's מטלטלין metaltelin and if somebody were
to worship it, if you worship a mountain as עבודה זרה, Avodah
Zarah, it doesn't become forbidden. The גמרא Gemara makes a דרשה, derasha,
אלהיהם על ההרים
ולא ההרים אלהיהם. Eloheihem al he-harim velo he-harim eloheihem. Their gods on
the mountains, the mountains aren't to be considered gods even if they're
worshipped. I mean, imagine what that would do if if you can
make the ground forbidden. It would make life pretty impossible. So only
things that are chattel could be forbidden. What about if you if
somebody were to worship a house? So רב Rav says that is
considered to be not מחובר לקרקע. mechubar le-karka. That's considered מטלטלין metaltelin
or maybe it's מחובר לקרקע mechubar le-karka but it's not קרקע, karka,
okay, it's not, and therefore it's מטלטלין metaltelin and therefore it becomes
forbidden. How is that relevant here? Because remember there's no מעילה me'ilah
by מחובר לקרקע. mechubar le-karka. So if you had the beam sitting
on the top of the of the sunroof and you were deriving
benefit in the case of the משנה, Mishnah, so it's still מטלטלין.
metaltelin. It's just sitting there, it's not connected to the ground. But
the גמרא Gemara says not actually interesting in the משנה, Mishnah, but
the גמרא Gemara said but the גמרא Gemara says we have just
implicitly assumed that if you build it into your house, that is
מעילה. me'ilah. Well, why is that מעילה? me'ilah? It's מחובר לקרקע, mechubar
le-karka, right? So again, this isn't really a question from the משנה
Mishnah because they've just said the משנה Mishnah is talking that it's
loose. But according to their assumption in their question, we have assumed
that once you build it in there will be מעילה. me'ilah. Why
is that? Isn't it מחובר לקרקע? mechubar le-karka? This proves רב Rav
that something that is built into the ground is still considered to
be מטלטלין, metaltelin, chattel, and therefore there still is מעילה. me'ilah. Okay,
so that's the גמרא's Gemara argument. So let's see what the גמרא
Gemara says. אמר רב אחא בריה דרב איקא, Amar Rav Acha berei
de-Rav Ika, no, הנאה הנראה לעינים אסרה תורה. hana'ah hanira la-einayim asrah
Torah. This is different because it's very visible הנאה. hana'ah. Now what
does that mean? This basically sounds like and the
מפרש meforesh here says
it in it. It basically sounds like even though it's true it's
מחובר לקרקע, Mechubar lekarka, because it's very obvious and evident, it's still
going to be מעילה. Me'ilah.
Was it obvious and evident?
I have no idea. You know, these הלכות halachos about מחובר לקרקע
mechubar lekarka are very like formalistic things; they tend to be categories.
Technically there's no מעילה me'ilah here, there is מעילה me'ilah there, right?
It's a categorical type of a thing. What difference does it make
how visible it is? I really find this answer, like, I don't
begin to understand it,
unless somehow what it's saying is that the reason that מחובר לקרקע
mechubar lekarka there's no מעילה me'ilah in general is because, you know,
if something is attached, how do I get הנאה hana'ah from things
that are attached? What do I do? I sit in the shade
of a tree? I scratch my back on a house? Like, you
know, there's not, it's not as obvious and evident an act of
appropriating when something is attached. So maybe here it's saying, but if
it's evident enough it is a problem. But again, why is this
more evident than the other cases? Maybe it's more evident not because
I'm getting the הנאה hana'ah sitting under it, maybe it's more evident
because I've actually built it into my house, and maybe that's what
the גמרא Gemara is saying. But that seems right, that seems to
be making though a different point. That seems to be making the
point that it wasn't מחובר mechubar beforehand. And let's read the next
line of the גמרא. Gemara. But הנאה הנראה לעיניים hana'ah hanireh la'einayim
is a very strange answer. Let's read the next line of the
גמרא. Gemara.
Wait, I'm sorry, so they're saying that
I'm trying to understand what you're saying.
So meaning, like, normally this would be considered מחובר, mechubar, but it
still is מעילה me'ilah because it's very evident here, obvious. But סוכה
Sukkah is obvious, so it seems to be saying that the whole
problem of מחובר לקרקע mechubar lekarka is that it's not as obvious
הנאה, hana'ah, and somehow this is more obvious הנאה. hana'ah.
So but we say that if you scratch yourself on a house
you're המקדיש, hamakdish, then that would be מעילה? me'ilah?
No, according to this, they're saying not. Generally, it would be considered
מחובר לקרקע mechubar lekarka and it wouldn't, unless you put that in
a category of הנאה הנראה לעיניים, hana'ah hanireh la'einayim, which I don't
know what falls into that category. Okay, so let's keep on reading
a little bit. So that seems to, that seems to be a
very strange answer. So let's keep on reading. לימא מסייע ליה, Leima
mesayei lei,
so let's try to support this idea that there is מעילה me'ilah
by a house. הדר בבית של הקדש כיון שנהנה ממנו מעל, Hadar
bevayis shel hekdesh kivan shehana mimenu maal, that's very straightforward.
If you live in a house that belongs to the הקדש, Hekdesh,
once you live in it and you get, you know, a פרוטה's
prutah worth of rent benefit from the house, you know, what you
would pay for rent, so then you've been מועל. mo'el. So you
see, it's considered not מחובר לקרקע, mechubar lekarka, it's considered מטלטלין. metaltelin.
אמר ריש לקיש התם בשקדשו ולבסוף בנו. Amar Reish Lakish hatam beshikdesho
ulevasof benao.
That doesn't prove this הנראה לעיניים nireh la'einayim idea. That could be
an, that could be the reason there's מעילה me'ilah is because first
the construction material was sanctified and then it was built into the
house. So not only did it start its life as מטלטלין, metaltelin,
it started its when it was קדוש, kadosh, it was קדוש kadosh
as מטלטלין, metaltelin, and therefore that status of fit for מעילה, me'ilah,
right, when it was sanctified as beams and stones, and then it
was fit for מעילה me'ilah at that stage, it was מטלטלין. metaltelin.
So it remains fit for מעילה, me'ilah, it remains a candidate for
מעילה me'ilah even after it's built into the house.
But were they saying that there was no מעילה me'ilah when you
were building it? Let's say it was not just construction materials,
maybe it would be, that has to do with the נפש nefesh
of the עבירה, aveirah, right, maybe it would be. But here it
was talking about that הקדש Hekdesh built the house and then you
went and you lived in it. אבל בנו ולבסוף הקדישו, Aval benao
ulevasof hikdisho,
first it was built and then it was sanctified, so the גמרא
Gemara says מאי, mai, what would you say, לומר, lomar, that there's
no מעילה? me'ilah? Then if that's true מה איריא דתני הדר בבית
שבמערה לומר, mai ira de'tani hadar bevayis shebamearah lomar,
why did then the end of the ברייתא Braita run to say
the case that if you lived in a cave there's no מעילה
me'ilah because that's clearly מחובר לקרקע, mechubar lekarka, right, the whole cave?
So even if somehow it's on הקדש's Hekdesh property, right, a הקדש's
Hekdesh owned cave, there's no מעילה. me'ilah. Why couldn't you give another
example, לימא הדר בבית של אבנים שבנאו ולבסוף הקדישו לומר, leima hadar
bevayis shel avanim shebenaho ulevasof hikdisho lomar, even in a case of
a stone house, if you first built it and then sanctified it,
לומר, lomar, there's no מעילה. me'ilah. If that's really true, give that
as a case, that even sometimes a stone house there's no מעילה.
me'ilah. So the גמרא Gemara says אמרי היא פסיקא ליה והא לא
פסיקא ליה, Amri hai psikah lei ha lo psikah lei, it would
rather give a case that's categorically there's no מעילה. me'ilah. A cave
there's categorically no מעילה, me'ilah, rather than to start discussing the case
of a stone house where sometimes there is, sometimes there isn't. If
it's looking to say there isn't, it wants a case that there
never is מעילה. me'ilah. Okay, which again, so now what the גמרא's
Gemara's answer really is, is there מעילה me'ilah by a house? So
the answer seems to be either one or two or combination. The
answer is yes. Why? Either because living in a house is somehow
considered נראה לעיניים nireh la'einayim and when it's נראה לעיניים nireh la'einayim
somehow there's we don't care about מחובר לקרקע, mechubar lekarka, which is
a very strange answer. And if that were true, why would the
cave be any different? The cave is just נראה לעיניים nireh la'einayim
as the benefit of living in a house. Okay, or so the
other answer which seems much more satisfying is that if this started
its life as מטלטלין, metaltelin, as קדוש, kadosh, and therefore as a
candidate for מעילה, me'ilah, then even though now it's in your house
and now you're benefiting from the beam built in your house because
you're living under it, but... the beam is something that still is
in the category of מעילה me'ila because it started as being sanctified.
So that's one answer and the other answer is just straight position
of רב. Rav. רב Rav would say, I always consider things that
start as מטלטלין metaltelin and later are built as מטלטלין. metaltelin. So
for רב Rav there's no question and even if you disagreed with
רב, Rav, the more satisfying answer is because you sanctified it first.
Okay and if you'll notice the רמב״ם, Rambam, you can just tell
by where the little letters are, the רמב״ם Rambam completely ignores the
answer of הנאה הנראה לעיניים hana'ah hanireh l'eynayim and he brings again,
it's just crazy, it violates categories and he basically makes the more
formalistic distinction about when did you sanctify. But even with the מטלטלין,
metaltelin, am I not also actually deriving benefit, living in the house
as opposed to you know, right, but not if I change it
right, by building by physically building my house? That that again, that's
interesting because you would have said that that yet even without living
under it. The גמרא Gemara is unclear on that point but the
answer might be yes you know once you get מעשה קניין דבני
ליה ma'aseh kinyan d'banei lei so it sounds like yes. Okay just
a few terms here. מחובר לקרקע Mechubar l'karka is attached to the
ground. What is מטלטלין? metaltelin? Chattel. And what is הנראה לעיניים? hanireh
l'eynayim? Visible, you know, it's a type of obvious and visible benefit.
So in the end what we see is is that this משנה
Mishna again to repeat seems to be is the core משנה Mishna
about מעילה me'ilah of stealing although again if you wanted to you
could redefine it as הנאה hana'ah and the giving to the friend
is you give benefit to the friend but it seems to be
that it's about stealing and then the question is how do you
define an act of stealing from הקדש hekdesh if you have a
right to handle the property it's harder you have to get it
out of your possession and then again you know and then finally
addressing this whole issue about what's defined as something that is ground
versus chattel and something that starts as מטלטלין metaltelin or maybe even
was sanctified as מטלטלין metaltelin there still would be מעילה me'ilah for
that. Okay so now that we are done with the basic acts
of מעילה me'ilah we turn to the next פרק perek which is
about the idea of a שליח shaliach about because if you'll remember
and this is the last פרק perek if you'll remember the final
point that was taught in a ברייתא Baraisa we learned about two
days ago is that by מעילה me'ilah שליחות shlichus is meaningful. Normally
if I send somebody to do an עבירה aveira it's my עבירה
aveira not their it's their עבירה aveira not mine, אין שליח לדבר
עבירה. ein shaliach l'dvar aveira. By מעילה me'ilah actually if somebody does
it it is considered my עבירה aveira and there is a certain
conceptual similarity here, the same way if I take oil and I
anoint Michael it's my מעילה me'ilah I took it even though he's
the recipient. If I tell my שליח shaliach to go get something
and he gets it I'm still sort of the one that is
the causal factor of this thing having happened so even though normally
we focus more on the act here there is more of here
there is more of this concept of שליחות shlichus and being a
causal factor actually can suffice. So let's take a look at how
the גמרא Gemara at how the משנה Mishna describes this case. I
also want to remind you that the normal case of מעילה me'ilah
that we're talking about is that you're בשוגג beshogeg right and that's
the case you bring a קרבן korban and a fifth so we're
not talking about that somebody is intentionally trying to steal from הקדש
hekdesh the person actually under misbelieves that this object is his okay
and that's the standard case. Let's look at the משנה. Mishna. השליח
שעשה שליחותו בעל הבית מעל. Hashaliach she'asa shlichuso ba'al habayis ma'al. If
the שליח shaliach does exactly what the house owner the person sending
him because it imagines mostly the שליח shaliach would be like a
servant so if he does what the house owner what the person
sending him told him to do he does his agency then it
is the מעילה me'ilah of the בעל הבית ba'al habayis there is
this concept of שליחות. shlichus. לא עשה שליחותו Lo asa shlichuso if
he violated the terms of his שליחות shlichus of his agency then
השליח מעל hashaliach ma'al then it's his action not the not the
sender's action and he was the one that was מועל. mo'el. כיצד
Keitzad what's an example? אמר לו תן בשר לאורחים. Amar lo ten
basar l'orchim. So here as I said it basically sees the standard
case of שליחות shlichus as an attendant or servant to the owner
to the homeowner so this he you're you know what is it
called you're entertaining guests and you go and you say to your
assistant go give the meat to the guests okay and that meat
happens to be קרבן korban meat you didn't realize it somehow I
don't know exactly how you got in your house because the only
קרבן korban meat that there's מעילה me'ilah would be בשר קדשי קדשים
basar kodshei kodashim no not בשר קדשי קדשים לפני זריקת דמים basar
kodshei kodashim lifnei zrikas damim or it could be עולה olah עולה
olah meat. So somehow you got עולה olah meat in your house
I don't know how okay so you and now you say you
say go give go give meat you think it's סתם stam meat
you say to your servant or assistant go give it to the
guests. Wouldn't wouldn't whoever took the meat out of the בית המקדש
Beis Hamikdash have committed מעילה me'ilah already? Well that goes to the
question again about נתנו לחבירו nasno l'chavero but maybe or maybe they
weren't taking it with the intention to possess it I don't know
how again I don't know exactly how it happens the act of
taking it out is not מעילה me'ilah the act of stealing is
מעילה me'ilah so somehow it got out of the בית המקדש Beis
Hamikdash יצאו ויוצא v'yeitzu v'yotzei okay but it doesn't matter. So if
you totally don't know and didn't have a reason to know, then
you're אנוס. onus. But if you're a standard case is שוגג, shogeg,
which is case where you had somehow reason to know or you
knew once and you forgot, but even though you don't know at
this moment, you thought you were taking שלמים shelamim meat out and
you took עולה olah meat out. I guess it could be that
case. Okay, so ונתן להם כבד. venasam lahem kaved. Now the שליח
shliach went and he gave them a liver, the liver from the
meat. כבד. kaved. He said give them liver, ונתן להם בשר venasam
lahem basar and he gave them meat. So השליח מעל, hashliach maal,
so the שליח shliach is the one that did the מעילה me'ilah
because a liver is not meat. When you said meat, you intended
to mean the normal meat, not internal organs. And therefore, if the
שליח shliach changed it from liver to meat or meat to liver,
he's doing his own thing, he's not listening to you, and therefore
it's his sin, he was מועל. moel. אמר לו תן להם חתיכה
חתיכה, amar lo ten lahem chaticha chaticha, let's say you said to
your assistant, give each person one piece of meat. והוא אמר טלו
שתים שתים, vehu amar tlu shtayim shtayim, and he said to them,
here, take two everybody. והם נטלו שלוש שלוש, vehem natlu shalosh shalosh,
and they all took three. So that sounds like a standard Jewish
meal. Okay, so כולם מעלו, kulam maalu, everybody did מעילה, me'ilah, because
the בעל הבית baal habayis did מעילה me'ilah because the first piece
was following the בעל הבית. baal habayis. The שליח shliach did מעילה
me'ilah because the second piece was his own, and the אורחים orchim
did מעילה me'ilah because the third piece was them acting on their
own. So everybody did מעילה me'ilah here. Now again, I should say,
it sounds like the מעילה me'ilah is even before anybody has put
any meat in their mouths, right? Because it sounds like the מעילה
me'ilah is again this act of taking, which gets back to the
previous משנה Mishna about the case about the beam and so on,
that it's the act of taking which is a form of מעילה
me'ilah as well. Let's take a look at the גמרא. Gemara. So
גמרא Gemara starts like this. מאן תנא דכל מילתא דמימלך עליה שליח
תרתי מילי הויין, man tanna dechol milta demimlach alei shliach tartei milei
havyan, top of כ"א ע"ב. kaf aleph amud beis. Who is the
one that says that anything that a שליח shliach would have to
ask about is considered a different thing? Meaning the גמרא Gemara assumes
that the idea of liver is, if you send your assistant to
the market and say, go buy me some meat, and they'll come
back and say, well, there's no meat, but there is liver, do
you want me to get liver? Okay, I usually think about it
as me calling up my wife and say, oh, they don't have
the brand you wanted, but they have this. Right? There's no meat,
but there is liver. So that's something he would ask about. He
wouldn't say there's no meat, but there's raisins. Okay, so that's something
which is somewhat in the same category, but you have to ask
about. So that's the idea of מימלך עליה שליח. mimlach alei shliach.
Something that you have to ask about. Is that also included or
intended? And this is, so we assume that liver is that nature,
and we're assuming that it's fundamentally a different thing. If you said
meat and he gave liver, or you said liver and he gave
meat, that he's not listening to you. So who is the one
that says that if a שליח shliach has to ask about it,
if you have to check if it's the right object, then we
define that as a different type of a thing? Okay, who is
that? So אמר רב חסדא דלא כרבי עקיבא, amar Rav Chisda dela
kerabbi Akiva, not like רבי עקיבא. Rabbi Akiva. דתנן, detnan, I think
this will make it a little bit clearer. הנודר מן הירק, hanoder
min hayerek, somebody made a vow that they're not going to eat
vegetables, or they forbade vegetables upon themselves. מותר בדלועין, mutar bedilu'in, you
can still eat gourds. Gourds aren't considered to be vegetables, certainly not
in the vernacular. ורבי עקיבא אוסר, veRabbi Akiva oser, רבי עקיבא Rabbi
Akiva forbids. Now, what you have to know is the end of
that משנה Mishna basically is that the חכמים chachamim say to רבי
עקיבא, Rabbi Akiva, how can you say gourds are vegetables? If you
send your שליח shliach to the market and say get vegetables, he'll
come back and say there were no vegetables, there were gourds. So
you see that they're not vegetables. So רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva said,
no, because he doesn't say there was no vegetables, there was meat.
He says there was no vegetables, there was gourds. So you see
they are vegetables. Okay, so that is the category of things the
שליח shliach would have to ask about. Are you okay with this?
They're close enough that you're asking, but they're not identical, so you
still have to ask. So the גמרא Gemara is saying it's assuming
that liver and meat have that quality, that if you say meat,
liver is in that grey zone, and therefore since our משנה Mishna
says you violate the שליחות shlichus when you do the other thing,
you see it's fundamentally considered like the חכמים chachamim who argue on
רבי עקיבא, Rabbi Akiva, fundamentally considered to be a different thing. The
same way gourds and vegetables are different, meat and liver is different,
like the חכמים chachamim who argue on רבי עקיבא. Rabbi Akiva. So
that seems to be the case. So אמר אביי, amar Abaye, no,
maybe it's even רבי עקיבא. Rabbi Akiva. אביי אמר אפילו תימא רבי
עקיבא, Abaye amar afilu teima Rabbi Akiva, it could even be רבי
עקיבא. Rabbi Akiva. Why? מי לא בעי אימלוכי? mi lo ba'ei imlochi?
Because רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva agrees that the שליח shliach has to
ask. Okay, so what does that mean? It means you can't compare
the נדרים nedarim question to the מעילה me'ilah question, because we're all
agreeing that when it comes to gourds and vegetables, or liver and
meat, it's a thing a שליח shliach asks about, right? So if
a שליח shliach asks about it, then it means that there's a
requirement in order for your doing your job that you would ask
about those questionable things, and that's the expectation, and for you to
ask and check in. Well, what happened in the case here where
he gave the liver instead of the meat? He didn't ask. So
that's violating his שליחות. shlichus. So even Rabbi Akiva would agree that
if you don't ask about it, you stepped outside of the bounds
of your שליחות, shlichus, you're supposed to ask. When it comes to
the נדר neder question, that's more a question about category. Do we
conceive of the stuff in the gray zone to be in the
category or out of the category? So the חכמים chachamim say it's
out, gourds are out, liver is out from meat. Rabbi Akiva says
it's in, right, you know, it's like fuzzy lines, you know, where
you distinguish the category. So within those fuzzy lines, Rabbi Akiva says
in, the חכמים chachamim say out, but that's a נדר neder question.
For a question of שליחות, shlichus, everybody agrees that when it's fuzzy,
you have to ask. And if you didn't ask, you stepped outside
of the שליחות. shlichus. Okay, so that's what Abaye says. Very nice
distinction. So let's take a look. תימרא רבנן קמיה דרבא teimara rabbanan
kamei d'Rava when the rabbis told over this discussion to Rava, אמר
להו amar lehu he said to the rabbis. רבנן rabbanan often means
like the students, you know, the unnamed rabbis, they're not the major
Amoraim. So they said over to Rava what Abaye had been saying.
Oh, he said, it's not exactly the same as the Rabbi Akiva
case. And he said to them, שפיר קאמר נחמני. shapir ka'amar Nachmani.
נחמני Nachmani was a name for Abaye, question whether it's his proper
name or a nickname. Some think that that's Abaye's proper name, that
Abaye was actually a later appellation. Anyway, he says, oh, that's good,
that makes sense, that distinction. He liked that. Wow, Rava agreeing, Rava
usually argues with Abaye. There you go. So that's the end of
that point. There's a difference between the question about are you within
the bounds of your שליחות shlichus and the question about whether it
is within the object being defined in the same category or not
in the same category. Now we are going to go on. מאן
תנא דפליג עליה דרבי עקיבא man tanna d'palig alei d'Rabbi Akiva now
we're going to sort of digress a little bit and discuss this
Rabbi Akiva issue, but obviously with a parallel to our Mishnah. מאן
תנא דפליג עליה דרבי עקיבא. man tanna d'palig alei d'Rabbi Akiva. In
that Mishnah about the gourd, we had that it's the unnamed חכמים
chachamim argue on Rabbi Akiva. Can we name the person who argues
on Rabbi Akiva? Who is the one who argues on Rabbi Akiva?
So the Gemara says, רבן שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel
he is, רבן שמעון בן גמליאל. Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel. דתניא detanya
we learned in a Baraita, הנודר מן הבשר אסור בכל מיני בשר.
hanoder min habasar assur bechol minei basar. Again a case about making
a vow. You vowed all meat is forbidden
to you, and you know, all meat becomes אסור, assur, all types
of meat. ואסור בראש וברגלים ובקנה ובכבד, ve'assur berosh uveraglayim uvekaneh uvekaved,
the head of an animal, and
the feet, the trachea, the liver,
ובלב uvelev the heart, all the inner, all the organs, ואסור בבשר
עופות ve'assur bevasar ofot it includes birds' meat, מותר mutar the one
thing that it's excluded is בשר דגים וחגבים, basar dagim vechagavim, fish
flesh and grasshoppers. That's not what people mean when they say meat.
But meat is everything else from fowl to בהמה beheimah and all
the parts of the animal.
That's the first opinion. That's implicitly Rabbi Akiva who says that even
though some of this you might have to check in about, it's
still within the category of meat. This is in Chullin? Yeah. Was
it? Yeah. I mean okay. I don't remember that, but okay. I'm
not seeing a cross-reference in Chullin either. But okay. Definitely the question
about birds versus grasshoppers and fish was in Chullin. I'm not sure
that this particular Baraita directly... Yeah, right, that's what I was saying.
Right, and we're going to get to that in a minute. רבן
שמעון בן גמליאל מתיר בראש וברגלים ובקנה ובכבד ובעוף ובדגים וחגבים. Rabban
Shimon ben Gamliel matir berosh uveraglayim uvekaneh uvekaved uve'of uvedagim vechagavim. Rabban
Shimon ben Gamliel says no, no, no. The head, the feet, the
trachea, the liver, the inner organs, and the birds, all those things,
and obviously also the fish and the grasshoppers, all those things are
not included in meat. Why? Because all those things are the things
that a שליח shliach would have to ask about. Right? There's no
meat, do you want inner organs? What do they call sweetbreads? Right,
do you want these things? All of this, that is the gray
area. And therefore, Rabbi Akiva says the gray area is in the
category, I say the gray area is out of the category. So
that is once again that debate, and here it's associated with Rabban
Shimon ben Gamliel. וכן היה רבן שמעון בן גמליאל אומר vechen hayah
Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel omer and to just emphasize the idea that
the inner organs are not the same as meat, קרביים לאו בשר
הן kirbayim lav basar hein inner organs are not real meat. Okay?
ואוכליהם לאו בר איניש ve'ochleihem lav bar inish and people that eat
them are not really human. Okay? So he said, you know what
they're good for? They're good for dog food. Okay? So people don't
eat inner organs. So he really said that they're not... Of course,
the problem is that that might make his point about the inner
organs stronger, but it undercuts a little bit his more theoretical point
because he doesn't want to say I'm just excluding things that are
so distant, he wants to say anything that's in the gray zone,
you know, is actually excluded. But okay. So now the Gemara says
like this, ולתנא קמא מאי שנא דבשר עופות משום דרגיל איניש דאמר
לא שכיח בישרא... u'letanna kamma mai shena de'basar ofot mishum deragil inish
de'amar lo shachach bisra... so why is bird flesh because it would
also exclude bird? Yeah. ובעופות. u've-ofos. Right. If you say meat, you
mean classic steak, you mean בשר בהמה, basar behema, you mean red
meat. If I wanted chicken, I would say chicken. I said meat.
Okay, so therefore for him meat is classic red meat and anything
else is you would have to ask about. But the חכמים Chachamim
say, fine, but even if you have to ask about it, it's
still in the same category. That's a debate of things you have
to ask about. So now the גמרא Gemara is going to say
why what do you know does it really make sense where you
draw drew the line. So let's read that again. ולתנא קמא מאי
שנא בבשר עופות u'le-Tanna Kamma mai shna be-vasar ofos why do they
say that bird, you know, chicken or whatever is in the category
because you'll ask about it. משום דרגיל איניש דאמר לא אשכח בישרא
דחיותא mishum de-ragil inish de-amar lo ashkhach bisra dikhiyusa the guy will
come back and say you know I didn't find animal meat I
didn't find that meat you know red meat ואתאי בישרא דציפרא va-asai
bisra detzifreh but I here look I've brought some chicken or do
you want or do you want chicken. So again it's this area
that gray zone and because it's the gray zone the חכמים Chachamim
say it's forbidden and רבן שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel
says it's מותר. mutar. But the גמרא Gemara said אי הכי i
hachi if that's true הכי נמי עביד איניש למימר לא אשכח בישרא
דחיותא ואתאי דגים. hachi nami avid inish lemaimar lo ashkhach bisra dikhiyusa
va-asai dagim. Somebody will say you know what I didn't find any
red meat but here I brought home some fish. What? At? I
know. It's to I think that the answer that it's a big
difference and I think this is what Charlie was referring to, you
know, we learned חולין Chullin and clearly the הלכה halakha you know
חז"ל Chazal found a reason to forbid chicken and milk and not
a reason to forbid you know fish and milk because chicken meat
although it's clearly not in the פסוק pasuk there's no חלב אמו
chalev imo by chickens right that has no mother's milk but nevertheless
it more is like you know red meat certainly than fish meat
is. So I really don't so I agree the question in my
mind does not make any sense but the גמרא Gemara here somehow
thinks that people will say that. Okay. I think that if people
will say that they'll say it really as an alternative. Look I
couldn't get any meat but I figured we would have fish tonight.
You might say it as an alternative. You wouldn't say it as
a substitute right? The chicken you'll say is a substitute. Alright so
anyways the גמרא Gemara somehow thinks it's a question. Let's see what
the גמרא's Gemara answer is. אמר רב פפא Amar Rav Pappa ביומא
דכוסא עסקינן. be-yoma de-chasa askinan. So לא אכיל איניש דגים. lo achil
inish dagim. We're talking about a day that you've let blood and
the day that you let blood people would only eat would not
eat fish. They would eat some you know real serious meat and
therefore in that day when you're talking about meat you clearly are
not thinking about fish because it's a day that you would never
eat fish. So the גמרא Gemara says אי הכי i hachi צפרא
נמי דאכלי tzifreh nami de-achli or some of the גרסא girsa say
לא נכלי lo nachli meaning if that's true people also don't eat
fowl on the day that they had bloodletting. People want some nice
red meat they want to get blood back in their system presumably.
Okay so so yeah you can't tell me oh it's the day
you let blood and therefore you're not thinking about fish and you
don't mean it by the word meat. You wouldn't mean you wouldn't
mean chicken by the word meat either on that day. דאמר שמואל
de-amar Shmuel דמסוכר de-mesuchar if somebody has some blood let from the
shoulders ואכל צפרא ve-achal tzifreh and you eat fowl פרח ליביה כצפרא
parach libei katzifreh your heart will fly away like a bird which
basically means it's not good for you. Okay. You'll get arrhythmia. Right.
So your word meat on that day would only mean red meat
and that would not be a good answer. והתניא ve-hatanya we also
taught in a ברייתא braita אין מקיזין דם לא על הדגים ולא
על העופות ein makizin dam lo al ha-dagim ve-lo al ha-ofos you
don't let blood on but how presumably here means that you're going
to afterwards eat fish or fowl ולא על בשר מליח ve-lo al
basar maliach or also that after eating salted preserved meat. You need
like fresh meat after letting blood. Okay so אלא ela it can't
be that answer that you have let blood because then you would
the only thing you would mean in that day by meat is
red meat. אלא אמר רב פפא Ela amar Rav Pappa ביומא דכאיבי
ליה עיניה עסקינן be-yoma de-kaivei lei einei askinan דלא אכיל דגים. de-lo
achil dagim. We're talking about a day that your eyes are hurting
and that people would not eat fish when their eyes were hurting.
So on that day when you said meat the only thing you
would have meant would have been chickens and you know and steaks
you know and some red meat you wouldn't have meant fish. But
again I find the whole question very difficult. It's so clear that
just in terms of you know the natural way we act we
think fish is very categorically different from chicken and red meat and
you see it by חז"ל Chazal forbidding chicken and milk and not
forbidding you know you know fish and milk. So anyway but the
גמרא Gemara somehow thinks it's an issue. All of that was a
digression from the idea to from pointing out that liver is different
from meat and therefore the שליח shaliach regardless of how you hold
by נדרים nedarim is it the same category or different certainly it's
something he needed to have asked about and by not asking he
violated the terms of the שליחות shlichus and therefore it's considered to
have been acting on his own. So now let's just finish this
up about the second case now about you say one he offers
two and everybody takes three. So so אמר רב amar Rav It
sounds like if somebody did more than you sent them for, the
שליחות shlichus is still is still valid for the part they were
doing. Okay, which is the case. You said one, he did two,
why don't we just say two is completely different from one, right,
and therefore I don't want it, I don't want it, and therefore
he's not a שליח shliach at all even in the first one.
So this is, therefore what? And therefore he's the only one that's
מועל, moel, you're never מועל. moel. He's not doing your job, he's
not doing your, you know, your bidding for one, he's completely doing
his own thing. Okay, now this is actually a very relevant area
question not just for מעילה, me'ilah, but גמרא Gemara asks it in
כתובות. Kesuvos. I go ahead and I tell somebody, can you go
go buy me an acre of land? And they went to go
ahead and they buy two acres of land. Okay, so is this
sale binding for the first acre? Or do we say no, he
did his own thing, maybe he owns the two acres, but I
don't own anything, right? Or do we say no, you know, for
the first acre at least he was acting for me and the
sale still is binding. Now of course there could be differences about
things that theoretically could be distinguished like if I tell you go
to the store and buy me, you know, right, two pieces of
meat, one piece of meat and you buy me two, right, we
would assume that for the first piece of meat fine, the other
one is your responsibility, you pay for it or you take it
back. Okay, but anyway that's exactly the גמרא's Gemara question.
Are you still a שליח shliach for the first thing that is
what was asked for even when you step beyond, you know, you
do more than you were set? So doesn't this seem like you
do remain a שליח? shliach? So the גמרא Gemara says,
says רב ששת, Rav Sheshes, no, maybe it's a special case.
דאמר שליח טול אחת מדעתו ואחת מדעתי. d'amar shliach tol achas mida'ato
v'achas mida'ati. No, maybe the שליח shliach is very explicit and he
says, right, he doesn't presume to be acting for you at all
in beyond the first one. So what he says is, right, if
I send Michael to buy an acre and he goes and he
buys two acres, but he says, one acre I'm buying for Dov,
the other acre I'm buying for myself, of course that's good. So
the גמרא Gemara says, or the taste of the steaks, he buys
one steak for me, one steak for him, it doesn't affect what
I sent him to do. So the גמרא Gemara says that's the
case here. That's what, well we'll see that the שליח shliach says,
the שליח shliach says to them, here's what the בעל הבית ba'al
habayis is offering one, but you know what, go ahead, take another
one on me. Okay, so he makes it very clear that the
first one is being done for the בעל הבית ba'al habayis and
the second one he's doing on his own. So מהו דתימא, mahu
d'teima, I might have thought עקר שליח שליחותיה דבעל הבית, akar shliach
shlichusei d'ba'al habayis, that even in that case once you're doing, once
you're violating, once you're going and doing stuff on your own, then
that makes you seen as completely acting on your own, and the
בעל הבית ba'al habayis is not מועל, moel, קא משמע לן, kamashmalan,
no. Now of course as Michael says, you know, that's not as
big of a חידוש. chiddush. And it's certainly true that the פשט
pshat of the משנה Mishnah is is that even when he presents
both of them for the בעל הבית, ba'al habayis, that he still,
that that does not completely, that does not undermine the שליחות. shlichus.
That when you add, the שליחות shlichus still remains as long as
you're adding. That's the simple sense, but the גמרא Gemara makes it
into a special case. So we will continue with this tomorrow which
is the final concept of מעילה, me'ilah, the concept of שליחות, shlichus,
and as we're seeing mostly this case here is building on the
idea of מעילה me'ilah as a type of acquiring and taking possession
of, because here it's not yet dealing with הנאה, hana'ah, and what
happens when you go ahead and do that yourself or through a
שליח. shliach. To be continued tomorrow. Yes, we're going to do it
beforehand. We're going to do it before מנחה. Mincha. So Aviv is
going to do מנחה Mincha at 6:40.